CHRISTOPHER J HOWARD

Lino Lakes, MN 55014

LinkedIn: www.linkedin.com/in/howardchrisi | GitHub: https://survifit.github.io

SUMMARY

Experienced IT professional with extensive disaster management training and experience. Broad business, technical, and educational background that allows for quick adaptation to new systems and environments. Solid understanding of hardware, networking, security, business continuity, and disaster recovery concerns. Understands qualitative and quantitative analysis in complex systems and the need for clear, concise, and complete communication of any assessment.

TECHNICAL SKILLS

Tools: Linux (Debian & RedHat), Windows, Python, Bash, PowerShell, JavaScript, MS Office Suite

Databases: MySQL, SQL Server, MongoDB, Neo4J

BI Tools: Tableau, Esri Pro

RELEVANT EXPERIENCE

Disaster Cycle Services Volunteer American Red Cross Twin Cities Chapter

Aug 2018 - Present Minneapolis, MN

Support local and national disaster responses, with a primary focus on Information and Planning. In 2020, donated more than 2500 hours of volunteer time including 9 virtual deployments for disaster operations. Completed training on a variety of disaster response skills including logistics, sheltering, feeding, and family reunification as well as public affairs, government operations, disaster planning, and reporting requirements. Also completed FEMA training for ICS, NIMS, NRF, emergency management, planning, leadership, decision making, effective communication, developing and managing volunteers, and creating and running exercises (see below for course numbers)

Teachers Assistant Trilogy Ed. Services

Mar 2020 – Present

Minneapolis, MN

Support adult learners going through the 24-week Data Visualization and Analytics bootcamp at the University of Minnesota. Subjects covered include Excel, VBA, Python, R, JavaScript, SQL Databases, MongoDB / NoSQL, Tableau, Big Data, and Machine Learning.

IT Systems Engineer Nodus Inc.

Jul 2016 – Aug 2019

Minneapolis, MN

Provide full-stack support to clients with a focus on customer service. Maintain and develop web applications using PHP, JavaScript, HTML/CSS using Laravel or Codelgniter on a LAMP stack. Design and implement networks that allow clients remote access to critical systems without compromising security using hardware that fits the business needs and growth potential. Host websites and remote business applications on physical and virtual Linux or Windows servers.

Consultant 3 Associate Network Engineer Unisvs

Apr 2016 – Jun 2016

Oct 2013 – Mar 2016

Eagan, MN

Provided support and project management for IT infrastructure supporting the Unisys Cargo application. Managed maintenance and upgrade support for a network of over 100 servers plus network devices including Windows, Linux, Checkpoint, F5, Cisco, and IDS technologies. Responsible for FTP and SFTP servers and network automation using VBS.

Team Supervisor Team Lead

Mar 2007 – May 2011 Jan 2006 - Mar 2007

American Red Cross Biomedical Services

St Paul, MN

Phlebotomist in charge of daily operations for blood donations at multiple fixed sites around the Twin Cities. Supervised two blood donation centers and up to nine team members for the North Central region of the Biomedical Services side of the American Red Cross, Joined the IT department with desktop support responsibilities for over 600 users along with the Avaya PBX and Octel voicemail systems and multi-function printer and device management.

EDUCATION

Data Visualization and Analytics Certificate: University of Minnesota, Minneapolis, MN A 24-week intensive program focused on gaining technical programming skills in Excel, VBA, Python, R, JavaScript, SQL Databases, MongoDB / NoSQL, Tableau, Big Data, and Machine Learning.

BS, Management of Information Systems: Cardinal Stritch University, Milwaukee, WI

VOLUNTEERING

Remote Volunteer American Red Cross Global Disaster Preparedness Center

Feb 2020 - Present Washington, DC

Cleaning, analyzing, and creating reports on data supporting Red Cross applications used world-wide for disaster preparation.

CERTIFICATIONS

Security+:

CompTIA, December 2020

FEMA Independent Study Courses:

IS-100, IS-200, IS-700, IS-800, IS-120, IS-130, IS-235, IS-240, IS-241, IS-242, IS-244

Certified Associate in Project Management (CAPM):

Project Management Institute, March 2018

Network+:

CompTIA, January 2018 (Renewed December 2020)

Competent Communicator:

Toastmasters International, June 2011